{
  "reference_number": "13019",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is important to have a strong goal. Urgent action is required."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Stabilizing short lived gases is achievable - new technology may make it possible to go beyond this to net zero emissions in the\n\n future. Agriculture has not had strong goals set for change and while making progress it is important to maintain its role as an\n employer and contributor to the NZ economy as a whole"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "The firewall concept whereby meets its goals for domestic reductions of emissions but may also contribute globally is well thought\n through for a small country dependent on international relationships"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If zero net emissions could be achieved earlier than anticipated this should be strongly supported. Targets should not be delayed\n beyond 2050 or the amount of reduction reduced."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is important to have clear steps for each year with the aim of measured achievement for the short term (5 year) plans. But long term\n goals must also be planned for - so that subsequent governments have a clear tack to follow and the plans are not subject to political\n\n expediency and erratic changes by new governments"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "15 years is actually a very short period in terms of the extent of change required. If new technology or other favourable circumstances\n allowed the goals to be achieved early the subsequent plan (4th) could include further reductions"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As above, the shorter the time frame the less likely lower emissions than planned for can be achieved."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The social aspects is crucial and far more needs to be considered than fuel poverty. The social presumably includes cultural change\nand the understanding that information and technology etc are intimately connected with people's understanding of what is\nimportant in life, how life should be lived, and how everybody can come to see themselves as having an important contribution to\n\nchange and see it as creating opportunities rather than to be resisted"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change will be experienced locally and local government is crucial in all plans and needs to be adequately resourced"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "These are important functions. It will also be necessary for the advice and reporting to be available and able to be acted on by all\nsections of society, not just central/regional/local government. Attention to process and progress will be required across all sections\n\nto ensure government action doesn't lag. Open government will be more important than ever"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Needs more emphasis on social science expertise to assist conversion of knowledge into action and identify vulnerable groups within\n\nsociety and their needs. Communication and \"community engagement' sounds top down and so not able to engage in the ways\nrequired"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "it should be wholistic in approach"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Sharing information and acting jointly will be essential to making the degree of change required in a short time frame"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Urgency should not lead to overlooking social justice issues"
    }
  ]
}
